DOMINIC SILVA

ds.career@pm.me | LinkedIn | Portfolio

SENIOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

I have deep experience building UIs with React and other UI frameworks supplemented with proficiency in UI/UX design. As a senior dev, I have a hand in architecting web projects, designing & building out component libraries, defining APIs, and shaping & distributing business logic across application layers. As a team lead, I develop feature roadmaps, drive technical discussions, facilitate cross-functional collaboration, and educate & motivate my peers.

EDUCATION

STONY BROOK UNIVERSITY

Bachelor of Engineering, Engineering Science Class of 2014

EXPERIENCE

SPACE SAVER

Web Developer & Designer, Jul 2024 - Present

- Improved SEO and overhauled overall design increasing traffic over first 3 months and simplifying previously convoluted UX.
- Implement furniture configuration tool to reduce traditional over-the-phone discussions and streamline quote process.
- Produce marketing material and refine marketing strategy to garner more outreach and increase revenue.

IBM

Lead Front End Developer, Nov 2023 - Jun 2024

- Defined contribution & collaboration process for the UI component library and reduced associated tech debt items by 40% after 3 months of taking ownership.
- Developed strategy for more thorough A/B testing and user feedback mechanisms as features continued to migrate.
- Rewrote documentation outlining onboarding process, new coding & testing standards, and common developer tools resulting in a 90% reduction in redundant help requests from new-hires and junior developers.

Senior Front End Developer, May 2022 - Nov 2023

- Developed and implemented a migration plan for converting top 10% of critical app features from Angular 1.x to React 17 TS.
- Achieved a 60% decrease in average support ticket volume after redesigning and reimplementing primary onboarding features.
- Routinely contributed to IBM's open-source React component library that sees over 50K downloads per week.
- Led re-education effort during QE framework migration from Selenium/Java to Cypress/Javascript resulting in minimal help requests and a completion date 6 weeks ahead of schedule.

FREELANCE

Web Developer & Designer, Aug 2021 - May 2022

KASISTO

Lead Front End Developer, Sep 2020 - Jul 2021

- Developed migration plan to convert web portal from multi-page application to single-page application using Vue.js resulting in a dramatically improved customer experience and a more robust and sustainable project architecture.
- Devised UX solution for and led development of main Al-conversation module reducing related support tickets by ~75%.
- Promoted a scalable and extensible component architecture by spearheading development of custom component library.
- Upskilled junior and full stack colleagues by holding weekly educational meetings on front end technologies and design patterns.

HUBCAP

Co-Founder | Lead Front End Developer | UX/UI Designer, Feb 2019 - Apr 2020

- Accelerated development of vendor web portal by employing a scalable, layered architecture using Angular 2+ and Material-UI.
- Led implementation of core features for vendor web portal such as promo & menu creation, scheduling, and QR scanning.
- Worked closely with back end lead to define business logic, APIs, and full stack architecture.
- Collaborated with UI designer on iOS app design in order to accelerate production time and remain under budget.
- Designed and developed marketing website in open source, React based, Gatsby Framework and deployed with Netlify.

EXPERIENCE CONT.

FREELANCE

Web Developer & Designer, Sep 2017 - Sep 2020

- Designed, built, and deployed modern, cross browser compatible, and search engine friendly sites for a variety of clients utilizing site builders, standard web technologies, and UI frameworks like React 16+, Angular 2+, and Vue.js.
- Ensured reliable and secure website access for users by expertly configuring domains, SSL, and Linux servers using Apache,
 DigitalOcean, GoDaddy, and BlueHost.
- Collaborated with clients on creative design & vision, custom features, content writing, SEO, social media, and marketing needs.

THE ANSWER COMPANY

Web Developer, Sep 2017 - Sep 2020

- Identified and enhanced UX of under-performing features/pages, resulting in an 80% reduction in support tickets.
- Improvements include enhanced UX for high traffic pages, modularized UI components, establishing ADA compliance, and decreasing bounce rate by 40% on average across product pages.
- Signed off by implementing a simplified CMS using the Django framework and React 16 to streamline web page creation/modification, reducing developer reliance and overall operational burden.

VIEWTRADE

Full Stack Developer, Sep 2016 - Aug 2017

- Collaborated with design team to retrofit backoffice system by redesigning the UI, improving UX with more intuitive forms and UI flows, and refactoring legacy code.
- Contributed to development of new iteration of web portal using open source, React based, grommet UI framework.
- Implemented a more intuitive data visualization widget for ETF data on customer web portal using D3 library.
- Created more dynamic web pages using JSP Actions and Custom Tags to improve load times and provide a way of encapsulating code functionality.

TOOLS & SKILLS

Technologies

HTML, CSS3, Sass, Tailwind, Javascript (ES6+), Typescript,
Vue.js, React 16+, Angular 2+, Zustand, Vuex, Redux, RxJS, ApolloClient,
Webpack, Vite, Husky, JS/TSLint, Jest, React Testing Library, Cypress, Storybook,
Node.js, Express.js, Next.js, Python, Django, Java, Spring Boot,
MySQL, MongoDB, PostgresSQL, Redis, GraphQL, Socket.io
Docker, Kubernetes, AWS,
Figma, Adobe Suite, Mural, Draw.io

Concepts & Disciplines

UX & UI Design Patterns, Layered Architecture, REST, gRPC, Websockets, Test Driven Development, Project Management

Interests

Developer Experience Impact, Developer Tooling, Component Library Development, LLM/NLP, Browser Plugin Development, Game Dev

SIDE PROJECTS

MTA Real Time Countdown Display – React, Typescript

An implementation of an alternate design to the real time displays in the NYC subway system. It displays more arrival time data at once and in a more intuitive and modern way, utilizing overlapping 'cards', larger fonts, improved alerts, and animations.

Fertility Data Converter – Vanilla JS

A web tool for converting exported fertility data from other fertility tracking apps to the privacy-centric, open-source, drip.app format.

<u>Car Dealership App – Django, Express, React, Typescript, MongoDB</u>

A fully featured car dealership web application featuring a microservice architecture that utilizes AI sentiment tools for customer reviews. Django is used as the core back end framework, Express for API endpoints, both SQL & NoSQL databases for data storage, and React Typescript for the UI layer. A simple CI/CD pipeline is configured for basic linting and testing.